<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at the second trienniall visitation of the right honourable and right reuerend father in God, William Lord Bishop of London, holden at Keluedon in Essex: September. 3. 1631. By Nehemiah Rogers, pastor of Messing in Essex</title>
            <author>Rogers, Nehemiah, 1593-1660.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1632</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 75 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A10925</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 21198</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S116117</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99851334</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99851334</idno>
            <idno type="VID">16605</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A10925)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 16605)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1254:6)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at the second trienniall visitation of the right honourable and right reuerend father in God, William Lord Bishop of London, holden at Keluedon in Essex: September. 3. 1631. By Nehemiah Rogers, pastor of Messing in Essex</title>
                  <author>Rogers, Nehemiah, 1593-1660.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 30, [2] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by George Miller for Edward Brewster, and are to be sold at his shop at the signe of the Bible, at the great north doore of Pauls,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1632.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>The last leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Visitation sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-03</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-05</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:16605:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:16605:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED AT THE SECOND TRIEN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niall Viſitation of the RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND RIGHT REVEREND FATHER IN GOD, <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> holden at <hi>Keluedon</hi> in ESSEX: <hi>September.</hi> 3. 1631.</p>
            <p>By NEHEMIAH ROGERS, Paſtor of <hi>Meſſing</hi> in <hi>Eſſex.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>O Vtinam omnes qui alacres currunt ad Cathedram, tam vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giles reperirentur ad curam: <bibl>Bern. Ser. <hi>77.</hi> in Cant.</bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>George Miller</hi> for <hi>Edward Brewſter,</hi> and are to be ſold at his Shop at the Signe of the Bible, at the great North doore of <hi>Pauls.</hi> 1632.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="imprimatur">
            <pb facs="tcp:16605:2"/>
            <p>Recenſui hunc librum cui titulus eſt (<hi>A Sermon Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched at the ſecond Trienniall Viſitation of the R.H. R.R. Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in God,</hi> William <hi>L.B. of London, holden at Keluedon &amp;c.</hi>) (vnâ cum Epiſtolâ Dedicatoriâ ad Venerabilem vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum Arthurum Duck Legum D. &amp;c.) qui quidem liber con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinet quatuordecim folia, in quibus nihil reperio bonis mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ribus, aut ſanae doctrinae contrarium, quò minus cum vtili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate imprimatur, modo intra tres menſes proximè ſequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes typis mandetur.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>GVLIELM. BRAY <hi>Epiſcopo Londinenſi Capellanus Domeſticus.</hi>
               </signed>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Ex aedibus Londinenſ.</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>Decemb.</hi> 17. 1631.</date>
               </dateline>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:16605:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT WORSHIPFVLL ARTHVR DVCKE, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. of the Ciuill Lawes, <hi>Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellour to the Right Honourable and Reue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Father in God, WILLIAM Lord</hi> Biſhop of London, and one of the Maſters of his Majeſties high Court of Chancery.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Right Worſhipfull and moſt worthy Sir;</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>
               </hi> Make no other Apologie for my ſelfe in reſpect of the Publication, and Dedication of the enſuing Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon, then that which <hi>Dauid</hi> made to his brother <hi>Eliab</hi> (who raſhly iudged his forwardneſſe in comming to the battle to proceed from the pride and naughtineſse of his heart) <hi>Is there not a cauſe?</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 17.29.</note> Might it haue dyed the common death of other Sermons, it had beene dead and buried out of ſight, but loath I was that it ſhould ſuffer a violent, and an ignominious death through the falſe ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lumnies, and ignorant cenſures of ſome ill affected ſpirits,
<pb facs="tcp:16605:3"/>
and therefore I haue ſought life for it, that it may liue to the world, and ſpeake for it ſelfe.</p>
            <p>I preſent it to your Worſhip; <hi>Protection</hi> I deſire not, if it be truth deliuered, it is Gods, and able to defend it ſelfe; if error, it were an inſufferable wrong to abaſe ſo worthie a <hi>Patronage</hi> for the Defence of it; <hi>Acceptati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on</hi> I craue; and this your wonted and natiue courteſie, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether with the great reſpect you beare to the meanest of our Tribe, aſsures me of.</p>
            <p>In which confident expectation I binde my ſelfe,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Worſhips in my beſt Obſeruance, <hi>NEHEMIAH ROGERS.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:16605:3"/>
            <head>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>At the ſecond Trienniall <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſitation of</hi> THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE AND RIGHT REVEREND FA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>THER IN GOD, <hi>WILLIAM</hi> Lord Biſhop of <hi>London,</hi> holden at <hi>Keluedon</hi> in ESSEX: <hi>September.</hi> 3. 1631.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>TEXT. NEH. 8.4.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>And <hi>Ezra</hi> the Scribe ſtood vpon a Pulpit of Wood, which they had made for the purpoſe.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Here needeth not a <hi>Seer</hi> to diſcouer the myſtery, and meaning of a Text ſo plaine, eſpecially to ſuch an Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditorie, where are ſo many,<note place="margin">Iob 39.29.</note> whoſe eyes, like thoſe of <hi>Eagles,</hi> ſee things <hi>a farre off.</hi> The <hi>Sum</hi> and <hi>Subſtance,</hi> with the <hi>Connexion,</hi> and <hi>Coherence,</hi> are ſo obuious, that <hi>who ſo runs may reade.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="2" facs="tcp:16605:4"/>Worthy <hi>Nehemiah</hi> hauing repaired the walls, and bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken buildings of <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi> begins the <hi>Repaire</hi> of <hi>Religion</hi> (which was much decayed) and of <hi>Manners</hi> (which was much corrupted) amongſt that people. This he ſets vpon in this Chapter;<note place="margin">Matth. 7.</note> Firſt, (like a wiſe builder) laying a good foundation, and after, building thereupon. He begins this worke with reading, and expounding of the Law, the better to conuince the Iewes of their aberrations, and fai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lings, which he doth effectually. Take we notice of Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culars.</p>
            <p>Firſt, the <hi>Meeting of the Congregation,</hi> and aſſembling of the people,<note place="margin">i. e. ſimul vel con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corditer Lanat. in loc.</note> both men, and women, and all that could heare with vnderſtanding, <hi>euen as one man, verſe</hi> 1. They were no <hi>Schiſmatickes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Place,</hi> in the ſtreet before the water gate, <hi>verſe</hi> 3. openly, and publikely, not in a ſecret corner. It was no <hi>Conuenticle.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Prieſt</hi> who he was, together with his be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hauiour and carriage, <hi>verſe</hi> 4. which well became himſelfe, and place;</p>
            <p n="1">1. He <hi>Opened his booke</hi> in the ſight of all the people (be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing fitly ſeated to be ſeene) vpon the opening whereof, the people ſhew much reuerence, <hi>verſe</hi> 5.</p>
            <p n="2">2. He <hi>makes a Prayer</hi> before the Sermon, and begins with bleſſing <hi>the great God of heauen,</hi> whereat the people are zealouſly deuout, with lifted-vp hands, and bowed heads and bodies anſwering thereto, <hi>Amen, Amen, verſe</hi> 6.</p>
            <p n="3">3. He <hi>Reades his Text,</hi> giues the ſenſe of the words, and cauſeth the people to vnderſtand the meaning, <hi>verſe</hi> 7, 8. The like method with this vnder the Law, is obſerued by vs the Preachers of the Goſpell and may hence haue warrant.</p>
            <p>One of theſe branches (as you ſee) I haue choſe for my Text, which ſets forth vnto vs the <hi>Preacher</hi> with ſome principall <hi>Circumſtantialls.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Preacher is deſcribed by his <hi>Name,</hi> and by his
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:16605:4"/>
               <hi>Office.</hi> His <hi>Name [Ezra.]</hi> His <hi>Office [the Scribe.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Circumstantialls</hi> are two: <hi>Situs; Locus:</hi> His <hi>Site,</hi> Or the <hi>Geſture</hi> vſed <hi>[hee ſtood]</hi> The <hi>Vbi</hi> or <hi>Place</hi> Where <hi>[Vpon a Pulpit]</hi> which is ſet forth or deſcribed further by the <hi>Materiale:</hi> the <hi>Matter</hi> whereof it was made <hi>[of wood]</hi> and by the <hi>Finale;</hi> the <hi>End</hi> why it was made <hi>[for the purpoſe.]</hi> Thus you haue the <hi>Prieſt</hi> in his proper <hi>Predicaments.</hi> As you haue heard the <hi>Logicall Reſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lution,</hi> be pleaſed with like patience to attend to the <hi>Theo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>logicall Expoſition.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ezra the Scribe]</hi> Who this <hi>Ezra</hi> was;<note place="margin">Text.</note> of what <hi>Kin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred</hi> he came; what was his <hi>Learning;</hi> what his <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, &amp;c.</hi> wee reade <hi>Ezra</hi> 7. at large; here onely hee is deſcribed by his name <hi>[Ezra]</hi> and by his <hi>Learning [the Scribe.]</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of <hi>Scribes</hi> there were two ſorts: ſome <hi>Laicks;</hi> Others <hi>Clergie men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of the firſt ſort, there were two rankes: Some atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the <hi>King</hi> as his <hi>Secretaries,</hi> theſe were termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>the Kings Scribes,</hi> 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 12.10. 2 <hi>Chro.</hi> 24 11. Such were <hi>Sheia;</hi> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 20.25. and <hi>Shaphan,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 22.3.</p>
            <p>Others attended <hi>Publike Courts,</hi> and <hi>Conſiſtories,</hi> and were like our <hi>Publike Notaries,</hi> or our <hi>Clerkes of Aſſizes:</hi> Theſe were termed <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; <hi>the Scribes of the People, Matth.</hi> 2.4.</p>
            <p>The ſecond ſort of <hi>Scribes,</hi> were <hi>Gods,</hi> and belonged to the <hi>Clergie,</hi> they were called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Scribes of the Law.</hi> Theſe were <hi>Doctors</hi> and <hi>Expoſitors of the Law,</hi> being by Office to write, reade, and expound the Law, vnto the people, <hi>Luke</hi> 7.30. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.17.<note place="margin">Ezra. 7.6.</note> Such a one was this <hi>Ezra</hi> called, elſewhere <hi>Sophir Mahir,</hi> a prompt <hi>Scribe;</hi> and here <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>that Scribe;</hi> by way of excellencie, the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brew article Π like the Greeke Ο noting alwaies ſome eminencie, or ſpecialtie, in the partie ſpoken of.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Stood]</hi> A <hi>Gesture</hi> noting <hi>Subiection,</hi> and <hi>Seruice;</hi> vſed by the <hi>Prieſts,</hi> and <hi>Leuits</hi> in all their miniſtration, <hi>Deut.</hi>
               <pb n="4" facs="tcp:16605:5"/>
10.8. <hi>&amp;</hi> 17.12. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.5.7. <hi>Iudg.</hi> 20.28. And by the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets,</hi> who are in this reſpect ſaid to <hi>ſtand before the Lord,</hi> 1 <hi>King.</hi> 17.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 18.15. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 3.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.16. And by the <hi>Angels,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 18.18. <hi>Luke</hi> 1.19. So then, <hi>Gods Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters with great reuerence, are to doe ſeruice to God, and to his Church,</hi> 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 35.3. The <hi>Holineſſe</hi> of the <hi>Place; Weightineſſe</hi> of the <hi>Worke; Preſence</hi> of the <hi>People; Worthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe</hi> of the <hi>Perſon,</hi> whom we repreſent, require it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Vpon a Pulpit]</hi> The word <hi>Migdal,</hi> in the <hi>Hebrew,</hi> ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifies a <hi>Turret;</hi> In the <hi>Greeke,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>; which ſignifies a <hi>Tribunall High-ſeate,</hi> or <hi>Place. Suggestum</hi> in the <hi>Latine,</hi> hath the like ſignification. Such a Seate was erected and ſet vp for <hi>Ezra;</hi> therein he ſtood, and ſo <hi>was aboue the people, verſe</hi> 5. (As <hi>Solomon</hi> was, who made him ſuch a kinde of braſen ſcaffold and ſet it in the midſt of the Court of the Temple, when he bleſt the Lord, and the people, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.13.) This kinde of <hi>Chaire</hi> or <hi>Pulpit,</hi> did after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards grow more Common and in vſe, whence (I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue) that phraſe aroſe, of <hi>ſitting at the feet of another,</hi> as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> is ſaid to haue ſate at <hi>Gamaliels;</hi> And <hi>ſitting in Moſes chaire;</hi> that is, preaching <hi>Moſes Law,</hi> ſitting in the <hi>Chaire</hi> or <hi>Pulpit.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Reaſons for the erecting of it were eſpecially two; Firſt, that he might be heard, and vnderſtood. <hi>The Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of God is ſo to preach, and in ſuch a manner to deliuer his Meſſage wherewith he is ſent, as that</hi> (ſo much as in him lies) <hi>the knowledge of ſaluation, may from him be deriued to all that heare him, Luke</hi> 1.77 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, that he might the better ſee, and be ſeene of all, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 6.13. God hath placed the <hi>Starres</hi> high, the more commodiouſly to ſhine vnto vs: So his <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> in an eminent place,<note place="margin">Matth. 5.</note> that their light might bee more conſpicuous. <hi>We are</hi> (as it were) <hi>ſet vpon a ſtage, and made a gazing, ſtocke</hi> (ſetting aſide contempt) <hi>euen in reſpect of obſeruation to Men and Angels.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But whereof was this <hi>Pulpit</hi> made? <hi>[of Wood]</hi> ſaith the Text. <hi>Wood</hi>] not <hi>Gold,</hi> nor <hi>Siluer,</hi> nor ſuch like coſtly
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:16605:5"/>
matter; but <hi>of Wood. The dignity of the Clergie ſtands not in outward pomp and glory, nor doth the worſhip of God conſist in rich ornaments or glorious furniture. Idolatry</hi> and <hi>falſhood</hi> (ſaith a Reuerend Prelate of our Church) is commonly more gaudie and plauſible then <hi>Truth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>.</hi> Hall B. of Exceter.</note> which hates either bought, or borrowed beautie, and will abide none but na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue colours: That heart therefore which can for the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward homelineſſe deſpiſe the ordinances of God, is already aliened from true religion, and lies open to the groſſeſt Superſtition. You may remember what was ſaid of old by <hi>Boniface</hi> the <hi>Martyr, when the Church had woodden Chalices</hi> ſhe had <hi>Golden Priests,</hi> but after, when ſhee came to haue <hi>Golden Chalices</hi> (as in time of Popery) ſhee had <hi>Wodden Prieſts.</hi> But why touch I this? For if <hi>Superſtition</hi> made our Aduerſaries too <hi>Carefull,</hi> and <hi>Bountifull; Prophaneneſſe</hi> and <hi>Atheiſme</hi> hath made vs too <hi>Careleſſe.</hi> The ruines of Gods houſe; the Duſt, and Cobwebs, wherewith our Churches were be hung, before <hi>Authority</hi> (like the good huſwife in the Parable) ſent a broome,<note place="margin">Luk. 15.</note> ſufficiently confir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med this. God holds himſelfe contemned, when his Churches are defaced, and his Vtenſils not decently preſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued; ſee <hi>Pſal.</hi> 74. <hi>verſe</hi> 8.10.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made for the purpoſe]</hi> And yet no Command for it, nor for any other of thoſe <hi>Solemnities</hi> vſed after, <hi>verſe</hi> 6. in <hi>Moſes Law.</hi> So then; <hi>Meere humane inuentions in the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtantialls of Gods worſhip, are not therefore vnlawfull</hi> (though appropriated thereunto and (afterwards) ſuperſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſly abuſed) <hi>vnleſſe in ſome other reſpect ſome ſinfulneſſe be found in them.</hi> But this you will ſay is not for the pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>For the purpoſe]</hi> Then, or for <hi>Speech</hi> it was (for both waies the words may be read, and rendered) <hi>i. e.</hi> to reade and expound the <hi>Word of God,</hi> the <hi>Law of Moſes</hi> in; <hi>So that the Pulpit is not for ſhew but vſe.</hi> Nor yet for any vſe, but this vſe; not for a <hi>Stage</hi> to play our owne parts or prizes: Nor for a-<hi>Fence-ſchoole</hi> or <hi>Paſquill,</hi> in ſhew to bee zealous againſt ſinne, and intend little elſe thereby, but reuenge of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:16605:6"/>
priuate wrong. This is not <hi>the Purpoſe</hi> I dare ſay it was made for.</p>
            <p>Thus you ſee the Text, is as <hi>Full</hi> as <hi>Plaine:</hi> Variety of Obſeruation it would affoord, if a skilfull workeman had the handling of it, but I muſt doe as I may: Being to paſſe through the <hi>Straits of Time,</hi> I reſolue to pitch my thoughts vpon one generall <hi>Theſis</hi> which I thus lay downe:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>An</hi> Ezra <hi>well becomes a Pulpit, and a Pulpit him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>From the <hi>Theſis</hi> I ſhall deſcend to the <hi>Hypotheſis,</hi> and thus inferre:</p>
            <p>
               <hi>It is pittie that an</hi> Ezra <hi>ſhould want it, or it want an</hi> Ezra.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Matth 5.15.</note>To proue the former; Our <hi>Sauiour</hi> by that compariſon of lighting a Candle, and putting it in the Candleſticke makes it good: Whereto ſerues the Candleſticke, but for the Candle lighted? And where ſhould a lighted Candle be placed, but in the Candleſticke? <hi>Elders</hi> muſt be ordai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in euery Church, Acts</hi> 14.23. not <hi>Lay-El<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders,</hi> but <hi>Preaching Elders.</hi> And ſuch was <hi>Titus</hi> enioyned by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> to conſtitute <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in euery Citie, Tit.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>Againe, the <hi>Miniſter</hi> is the <hi>Watchman, Iſay</hi> 21.11. His <hi>Charge,</hi> and <hi>Pulpit,</hi> is his <hi>Watch-tower, Hab.</hi> 2.1. He is a <hi>Planter,</hi> and a <hi>Waterer,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3 6. His <hi>Congregation</hi> an <hi>Orchard,</hi> and <hi>Pleaſant Garden, Cant.</hi> 4 12 13. He is a <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.9. and a <hi>Seedſ-man, Mar.</hi> 4.14. His <hi>Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple</hi> are the <hi>Field,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor</hi> 3.9. Hee is a <hi>Maſon</hi> or <hi>Carpenter,</hi> 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.10. They are the <hi>Houſe</hi> and <hi>Temple,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.16. <hi>Quam benè conueniunt?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This alſo is the iudgement of our <hi>Church,</hi> which takes order by her <hi>Canons,</hi> not onely for the Examination of thoſe who are to be admitted into ſacred orders, that they be <hi>Ezra's, Apt Scribes;</hi> but likewiſe that euery one ſo ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted be prouided of ſome <hi>Place</hi> and <hi>Pulpit,</hi> either <hi>Benefice</hi> or <hi>Curatſhip,</hi> wherin he may employ his gifts, and attend the <hi>Cure of ſoule, Can.</hi> 33.34.35. So then, It is great pittie
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:16605:6"/>
(and men are neuer worſe then when they are pittied) that either ſhould be wanting to the other.</p>
            <p>I would direct the Application of this to three ſorts of men of higheſt quality, and ſort; <hi>Patrons, Prelates, Prieſts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Application.</note> and deriue Inſtruction hence of a Three-fold leſſon. To the one <hi>Care and Conſcience in Preſenting,</hi> To the Second, <hi>in Ordaining,</hi> To the laſt, <hi>in Executing and Officiating</hi> that where with they are betruſted.</p>
            <p>If you aske me the reaſon, why in many <hi>Churches,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1.</hi> To Patrons.</note> where are faire <hi>Pulpits,</hi> there are no better <hi>Pulpit-men?</hi> I muſt tell you, <hi>Corrupt Patrons</hi> are in greateſt fault. It is an ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſie matter for a man in a Corrupt age (though his gifts and endowments are ſo meane, as that no Calling in the World will affoord him Bread) to be well beneficed, <hi>aut errore Hominis, aut aere Simonis;</hi> while men giue vpon diſhoneſt termes, what man of parts dare accept thereof? Theſe refuſing, ſuch muſt be ſought for as will, <hi>Micha's Prieſt</hi> is welcome, ſo he will accept of <hi>Micha's Wages:</hi> If he haue Learning enough to vnderſtand, <hi>Quid dabis?</hi> and make an anſwer to it; And will bee contented with the like vſage which <hi>Dauids Embaſſadors</hi> found from <hi>Hanuns Princes,</hi> to haue their <hi>Garments cut off by the buttocks,</hi> and their <hi>Beards halfe ſhauen away</hi> by vniuſt <hi>Compoſitions,</hi> he is <hi>a Prieſt for the purpoſe.</hi> No wonder ſuch go in <hi>Short Cloakes,</hi> how can they goe in long? All the while they ſtay at the borders of <hi>Iericho,</hi> they cannot recouer their ſhame: The <hi>In-com</hi> was ſo great at their firſt enterance.</p>
            <p>If any ſuch be preſent as haue to doe with <hi>Preſentations</hi> to <hi>Church-liuings,</hi> let me beſeech them, <hi>euen as if Chriſt himſelfe did beſeech them,</hi> not to betray his Church into the hands of ſuch <hi>Blinde guides;</hi> When you Preſent, Preſent not to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Mother-Church</hi> a <hi>Prometheus</hi> ſacrifice, <hi>skin and bone, without fleſh.</hi> Let your <hi>Queſtion</hi> bee, as theirs in the <hi>Goſpell, Who is worthy?</hi> Preſent not <hi>Woodden Priests,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 10.11.</note> to make your ſelues <hi>Golden Patrons.</hi> Reſpect not <hi>Gifts</hi> of <hi>Gold,</hi> for the furniſhing of your <hi>Cup-boards,</hi> but <hi>Gifts</hi> of <hi>Grace</hi> for the furniſhing of the <hi>Pulpit.</hi> Beware of Crop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:16605:7"/>
the poore Miniſters maintenance; Let not out that Blood your Fore-fathers put into the Churches veines, vnder pretence of her falling into a <hi>Plurifie.</hi> Thinke not with <hi>William Rufus</hi> any longer, that <hi>Church-Bread</hi> is one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Sweet-bread.</hi> Take not away their maintenance with <hi>Iulian</hi> the <hi>Apostata,</hi> vnder pretence of Conſcience, that ſo much liuing is a Burden to them, and a Hinderance of their Miniſterie. Deale not with your <hi>Clerkes,</hi> as <hi>Dionyſius</hi> with his <hi>Gods</hi> to take away their <hi>Gold,</hi> and put vpon them <hi>Line<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſy-wolſey,</hi> as being <hi>Cooler</hi> for the <hi>Summer,</hi> and <hi>Hotter</hi> for the <hi>Winter,</hi> and then (which is worſt) hauing their <hi>Liuings,</hi> flout at them for their <hi>Pouerty;</hi> like the <hi>Iewes</hi> who hauing ſpoyled <hi>Chriſt</hi> of his <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſtments,</hi> then mocked him with <hi>Baſeneſſe.</hi> Forget not thoſe <hi>Woes,</hi> denounced by our <hi>Saui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our</hi> againſt the <hi>Phariſees,</hi> for <hi>deuouring vp of widdowes hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> (much more for <hi>deuouring vp his Fathers</hi>) And let that <hi>Whip</hi> be thought vpon, vſed againſt <hi>Buyers and Sellers in the Temple,</hi> much more <hi>of the Temple,</hi> for if thoſe were whipt with <hi>Rods,</hi> then theſe with <hi>Scorpions.</hi> In briefe; re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member, if the <hi>Nurſe</hi> wants <hi>Bread,</hi> the <hi>Childe</hi> wants <hi>Milke;</hi> both <hi>Cry,</hi> both are <hi>Heard,</hi> woe to that man that hath the <hi>Cry of ſoules</hi> againſt him.</p>
            <p>But if no ſuch Miniſters were made, how could they be preſented?</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">2. <hi>To Prelates.</hi> 1 Tim. 5.22.</note>True; therefore the Charge is great which is laid vpon <hi>Prelates in Ordaining,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, &amp;c. but to Proue firſt, and to vſe a very preciſe Examination, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore they ſeparate any man to the Office of a Miniſter: And yet in the Choyſeſt Elections,<note place="margin">2 Sam. 18.19.20.21.</note> they may be deceiued. Som<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times it fareth with our <hi>Gouernors,</hi> as it did with <hi>Ioab</hi> in the Campe,<note place="margin">Verſe 22.</note> 2 <hi>Sam.</hi> 18. <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> offers himſelfe to bee the caryer of tidings, but is put backe, and <hi>Cuſhi</hi> taken, as fitter for the ſeruice; Still <hi>Ahimaaz</hi> importunes <hi>Ioab,</hi> and through importunity preuailes to run after, and (taking the way of the Plaine) outruns <hi>Cuſhi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">23.</note> and comes firſt to <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid,</hi> as if he had great matters to impart vnto the <hi>King,</hi> but being examined on particulars, he could giue no other an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:16605:7"/>
but this, <hi>hee ſaw a great tumult,</hi>
               <note place="margin">29.</note> 
               <hi>but knew not what it meant.</hi> So it may be ſome (ſuch is the raſhneſſe of youth) ſtepping in, and putting themſelues forward, may through importunity, obtaine that which their deſerts could neuer, and ſo (taking the way of the Plaine) (the beaten path of Simony) ouergoes the Worthyer, but when he comes to deliuer his meſſage, like him in the Goſpell <hi>he is ſpeechleſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">30.</note> and his entertainement like that of <hi>Ahimaaz, Turne aſide, ſtand thou by.</hi> This (I ſay) may be an ouerſight: But for the moſt part, the fault is amongſt our ſelues: A Biſhop may examine a man as concerning Learning, but can any Biſhop know the <hi>Life</hi> and <hi>Conuerſation</hi> of euery one that is to be admitted into holy orders, otherwiſe then by the the teſtimonie of thoſe that know them? Now if the firſt Concoction bee bad, can the Second, or Third be good? <hi>Ministers, Gentlemen,</hi> and Others, ſhould not for fauour, nor by-reſpects, be too liberall of their hands, in giuing teſtimoniall of any, whom they either know not, or elſe not to be well deſeruing. The ſetting to a raſh hand here, is as the raſh laying on of hands, and (though wee bee no Prelates) a tranſgreſſion of the Apoſtles precept. If then thou knoweſt thy <hi>Friend</hi> bee fit, or thy <hi>Childe</hi> bee fit, and canſt giue a teſtimony as Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> did of <hi>Demetrius,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Epiſt 3.12.</note> ſend him vnto <hi>Iairus the Ruler of the Synagogue;</hi> Otherwiſe let him follow that Calling he is fitteſt for. And anſwer him (be he friend or kinſman or any other) that deſires thy te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtimony for his preferme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as that famous <hi>Biſhop of Lincolne, Robert Grosthead</hi> did one, who earneſtly ſolicited him, in the behalfe of his poore kinſman, that hee would preferre him, and therupon enquiring what condition of life he fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed, and vnderſtanding that he had beene brought vp to husbandrie, anſwered; <hi>Then if his plough be broken I will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paire it, or rather then faile beſtow a new vpon him, but ſo to dignifie him as to hinder him in that courſe and calling wherein he was brought vp, and whereto he is fitted, I meane not to do.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But I haſten to the Third and laſt Sort,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> To Prieſts.</note> whom this do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine doth eſpecially concerne, You my Brethren; of mine
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:16605:8"/>
owne <hi>Coate</hi> and <hi>Calling;</hi> the <hi>Select Subiect</hi> of this daies meeting, and diſcourſe, who are (as I conceiue) <hi>all Pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pit-men.</hi> And therefore I ſhall not need to call vpon you to get you Pulpits (as <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi> of old did vpon his hearers: to get them Bibles.) It is not wanting vnto you. The force of my <hi>Exhortation</hi> muſt bend this way, that you be not wanting vnto it, which you ſhall not bee, if you be <hi>Ezra's Prompt and Ready Scribes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And ſeeing I am to ſpeake to thoſe who are <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nderſtanding,</hi> it will doe well enough, though <hi>Omnia in figura</hi> (as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſpeakes in another caſe) and I keepe my ſelfe vnto the <hi>Metaphor:</hi> Commending thoſe Rules vnto you, which <hi>Good Pen-men</hi> giue in the Art of writing, applying them to our purpoſe as wee paſſe along.</p>
            <p>Theſe Rules are either <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Preparatorie,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, ſuch as Concerne the <hi>Worke it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The former ſort, reſpects the <hi>Pen;</hi> Or the <hi>Site</hi> and <hi>Cariage of the Body;</hi> Both are of vſe to vs.</p>
            <p>Firſt, for the <hi>Pen;</hi> the Care of a <hi>Good Scribe</hi> muſt bee to prouide one <hi>Fitting,</hi> both for his <hi>Hand</hi> and <hi>Paper.</hi> Next to the <hi>Holding</hi> of his <hi>Pen,</hi> leſt hee diſcouer himſelfe a Botcher.</p>
            <p>That his <hi>Pen</hi> may be <hi>Good</hi> and <hi>Fitting</hi> euery way, there is a double Care required; 1. In <hi>Chooſing</hi> of the <hi>Quill,</hi> that it be not too <hi>Hard</hi> nor <hi>Full of teeth.</hi> 2. In the <hi>Cut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, Riuing,</hi> or <hi>Nibbing</hi> of the <hi>Penn,</hi> that it may write <hi>hard,</hi> or <hi>ſoft,</hi> as Occaſion requires. Thus if we would write <hi>Well,</hi> and <hi>Faire,</hi> let vs not affect to be dealing with thoſe <hi>Scriptures</hi> that are <hi>Obſcure</hi> and <hi>Darke,</hi> Of <hi>Ambiguous,</hi> and <hi>Doubtfull meaning;</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Pet. 3.16.</note> Of which kinde, there are not a few in holy Writ, and none more ſubiect to bee wreſted and peruerted. (<hi>Wits</hi> making ſuch places, the <hi>Palaestra</hi> to proue maſteries in) You know the <hi>Antient Fathers</hi> did ſcarce touch the <hi>Booke</hi> of the <hi>Reuelation</hi> in all their wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, thinking it farre ſafer with ſilence, to admire, then to aduenture to expound it. Such then as faſten (to chooſe)
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:16605:8"/>
vpon ſuch darke Texts (except they haue the better parts and helps) ſeeme to write with the <hi>Ganders quill,</hi> and while men ſeeke to get the praiſe of a nimble head, and ſharpe wit by tying knots to vntie againe, they doe with the dog leaue ſoft meate, to knawe vpon the bones.</p>
            <p>But ſay in our ordinary lot and courſe,<note place="margin">Quest.</note> we meete with ſuch a Scripture, what muſt then be done?</p>
            <p>In ſuch a Caſe,<note place="margin">Reſp.</note> (to keepe me ſtill vnto the Metaphor) doe as good <hi>Penmen</hi> doe with ſuch a <hi>Quill,</hi> ſcrape it, and pare it, till you get away the <hi>Teeth</hi> what may be; I meane that you would <hi>Diſtinguiſh aptly</hi> that which is <hi>Confuſed;</hi> And <hi>Illuſtrate plainely</hi> that which is <hi>Obſcure:</hi> You know the Helps, the Vſe of <hi>Tongues,</hi> and <hi>Authors, &amp;c.</hi> And <hi>Prayer</hi> in ſuch a Caſe, is the Beſt Booke in the Studie: Enquire of him who is both the <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Interpreter</hi> of Scripture. The noiſe of <hi>Axe</hi> and <hi>Hammer</hi> would not bee heard (ouer-loud) within the <hi>Temple;</hi> the worke would be framed in <hi>Lebanon.</hi> To reckon vp all that wee haue read, with their ſeuerall opinions vpon ſuch a Text, is (in my poore conceit) with <hi>Dauid</hi> A ſpice <hi>of Pride</hi> in num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering of the people: As on the other ſide at no time to Quote an Author, may be thought with <hi>Rhehoboam</hi> to <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the iudgement of the wiſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To bee briefe, if after all our paines ſuch places remaine to vs ambiguous, and doubtfull, it is enough if we acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, confeſſe, and religiouſly admire: Not peremptori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly determining on either part, ſhutting vp our diſcourſe as the Iewes were wont, euery doubtfull place they met withall with this, <hi>Elias cum venerit ſoluet dubia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Or if in Caſe, we doe determine, it ſhall bee our wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, to walke in the beaten roade of the Church, and not to run out into any ſingle <hi>Paradoxes</hi> of our owne, to trouble the common peace: <hi>Better is it to bee last in the droue of good Expoſitors</hi> (ſaith our Reuerend Arch-biſhop in his Expoſition vpon <hi>Ionah) then to bee formoſt inventing our owne Conceits.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:16605:9"/>This is not all, for after wee haue Choſe our <hi>Quill,</hi> With the good Pen-man, we muſt be Carefull in <hi>Cutting</hi> of our <hi>Pen.</hi> This requires <hi>Skill,</hi> that it may be neither too <hi>Soft</hi> nor ouer <hi>Hard:</hi> Therefore the <hi>Apoſtle,</hi> ſpeaketh thus to <hi>Timothy, Shew thy ſelfe approued vnto God, a workeman that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly diuiding the Word of truth,</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2.15. Gods Miniſter, muſt <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Diuide</hi> and <hi>cut:</hi> A ſpeech borrowed from the Cutting vp of the <hi>Sacrifice,</hi> in which there was great skill required, the <hi>Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer</hi> muſt be left hanging on the <hi>Right ſide;</hi> the <hi>Heart</hi> and <hi>Lungs,</hi> vpon the <hi>Channell bone,</hi> the <hi>Milt</hi> vpon the <hi>left ſide;</hi> and the <hi>Kidneys,</hi> vpon the <hi>Rump.</hi> Each <hi>Bungler</hi> can Chop a Text into Gobbets; but ſo to Cut the word, as to giue euery one their Portion, and therein approue ones ſelfe to God, is the propertie <hi>Of a Workeman that needeth not to bee aſhamed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Of this, there are two parts; <hi>Reſolution</hi> and <hi>Applica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Former</hi> is as the <hi>Slitting</hi> or <hi>Riuing</hi> of the Pen; the <hi>Latter</hi> as the <hi>Nibbing</hi> of it.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Si Logica abſit, rationalis homo, praeter rationem in linguae ſono verſatur.</note>Our Text muſt be vntwiſted, and vnlooſed, or as it were vnbowelled, which cannot bee done without the helpe of <hi>Logicke</hi> (the hand of Philoſophie) This would not bee <hi>Ouer-ſlight,</hi> nor <hi>Ouer-curious;</hi> for <hi>Aequè confuſa eſt diuiſio &amp; nimia &amp; nulla</hi> (ſaith <hi>Fulgentius</hi>) To make a long <hi>Analyſis,</hi> to a Short <hi>Text,</hi> is with the Citizens of <hi>Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> to build <hi>Great Gates</hi> to a <hi>Little Citie,</hi> (who were well flouted for their paines) Or like the <hi>Boaſting Traueller,</hi> who comming to his Inne, plucks out great ſtore of coine, and ſpends but two-pence. And on the other ſide not to obſerue <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Order</hi> is as bad. A Burden well wrapped, and pack't vp together, wee carry with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter eaſe: both <hi>Minister</hi> and <hi>Hearer</hi> is much help'd by <hi>Method.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for the <hi>Applying part,</hi> reſpect muſt bee had vnto the <hi>Auditory,</hi> as the good Pen-man hath in nibbing of his Pen vnto the kinde of <hi>Paper</hi> he writes vpon, that it agree with
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:16605:9"/>
it. Some hath a hard and croſſe graine, which ſoone takes off the edge of a <hi>Tender Penn;</hi> here too much of the nib would not be left: The <hi>Penn</hi> would bee <hi>Hard</hi> and <hi>Dry.</hi> Some paper againe hath a more fine, and tender graine, with which the <hi>Smaller Penn</hi> doth beſt agree: Your Ordinarie <hi>Paper</hi> is <hi>Pot-paper</hi> of a middle nature, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quires, that the nib be neither too ſoft, nor too hard, but brought vnto a meane.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Gods Prophets,</hi> muſt fit themſelues to the <hi>Perſons</hi> they haue to deale withall, becomming <hi>all to all that they may ſaue ſome.</hi> A <hi>Nathans tongue</hi> ſuits well with a <hi>Dauid's heart;</hi> A <hi>Huldahs,</hi> with <hi>Ioſiah's;</hi> And an <hi>Elijah's</hi> and <hi>Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chajah's</hi> with <hi>Ahab's;</hi> A <hi>Iohn Baptist</hi> with <hi>Herod's</hi> doth beſt of all.</p>
            <p>It is worth our taking notice of, how God in all ages hath proportioned men to the occaſions: A <hi>Mild Moſes</hi> was for the low eſtate of <hi>Afflicted Jſrael: mild in ſpirit</hi> (ſaith one) but <hi>mighty in wonders: mild</hi> becauſe hee had to do with a <hi>perſecuted</hi> and yet a <hi>techie people; mighty</hi> becauſe he had to doe with a <hi>Pharaoh.</hi> A <hi>Graue</hi> and a <hi>holy Samuel</hi> was for the <hi>quiet conſistence</hi> of <hi>Iſrael;</hi> And a <hi>fierie-ſpirited Elijah,</hi> for the <hi>deſperateſt declinations</hi> of it. If in later times of the depraued Condition of his Church, God hath rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed vp ſome ſpirits, which haue beene more warme, and ſtirring, then thoſe of common mould, wee cannot cenſure the choiſe, when we ſee the ſeruice. (As a Reuerend Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late of our Church ſpeakes worthily.)</p>
            <p>One thing more (before I paſſe this) be pleaſed to take notice of; that how-euer you may ſeeme in the <hi>Nibbing</hi> of your <hi>Penn</hi> (through the ſloape holding of your knife in cutting it halfe way, to make it thinne, and then ſtrait ouer-thwart) to make Two-cuttings, yet if it be not done at once,, it will not write <hi>Faire</hi> and <hi>Currantly;</hi> So in all our <hi>Vſes</hi> and <hi>Applications</hi> deriued, and deducted, from our <hi>Doctrines</hi> (how euer they may ſeeme yet) let them not be <hi>Two,</hi> but <hi>One Syllogiſme</hi> and ordinarily a Connexe; Looke how many <hi>Vſes</hi> we deduce from the Doctrine deliuered, if
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:16605:10"/>
they will make a <hi>Syllogiſme</hi> (the Doctrine being the Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument) we miſſe not our <hi>Rule.</hi> And then will our <hi>Appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> be more effectuall.</p>
            <p>Nothing elſe remaines to be ſaid concerning the <hi>Making</hi> of our Pen. Only this (before I come to the Rules which concerne our Holding of it) we may doe well, to <hi>Try our pen</hi> hauing made it; See how our notes affect our ſelues: If our owne ſpirits are not moued with what we haue ſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>died, there is but little hope that thoſe who heare vs ſhould be affected with them.</p>
            <p>Our Pen thus fitted, our next Care is, that wee looke to the <hi>Holding</hi> of it: Which may not bee with the <hi>Fiſt</hi> too <hi>Slouenly,</hi> nor yet betwixt <hi>One Finger</hi> and the <hi>Thumbe</hi> too <hi>Daintily,</hi> or <hi>Nicely,</hi> but</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>With a Light and eaſie touch,</hi> not griped too hard; For thence ariſeth theſe two benefits; <hi>The Command of the hand;</hi> And <hi>Quicke diſpatch of matter.</hi> Both Extreames would be auoided in the handling of holy things. It is not neceſſary wee ſhould haue <hi>All</hi> wee ſpeake in <hi>Print;</hi> and <hi>Weigh</hi> euery word as in a <hi>Ballance,</hi> for weight, and tuneable meaſure; Smooth Elocution, Fine Pronunciation, and the like, will ſoone bring vs into that veine of preaching, which <hi>Biſhop Latimer</hi> once blamed, vnder the wittie terme of <hi>Straw-berry preaching;</hi> and which S. <hi>Ierome</hi> doth ſo much deride in his Epiſtle to <hi>Nepotianus,</hi> telling him, that the Spirit of God came downe in the likeneſſe of an <hi>Innocent Doue,</hi> not <hi>Painted butterflie.</hi> Aſſure we our ſelues brethren, that as the rare and abſolute quality of the <hi>Pen,</hi> conſiſteth not in <hi>Painting, Pricking forth,</hi> and tedious writing of ſixe lines in a ſtudie, no more doth the <hi>Excellencie of Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching</hi> in the like exactnes. See 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14.15. Had the Fathers tooke this courſe, their workes had neuer beene in ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny large volumes as now we haue them.</p>
            <p>I grant yee; <hi>Accurate Sermons</hi> are fit for <hi>Learned Audi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tories:</hi> At ſuch a time as this, it will doe well, if they ſmell ſomewhat more of the lampe then ordinary; and in ſuch a caſe I could deſire with <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> to ſpeake, <hi>non modo
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:16605:10"/>
ſcripta ſed etiam ſculpta;</hi> But in our <hi>Common</hi> and <hi>Ordinarie Auditories,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. de doct. Chriſt. lib. <hi>4.</hi> cap. <hi>10.</hi> In Pſal. <hi>139.</hi>
               </note> there is (to vſe Saint <hi>Auſtins</hi> phraſe) <hi>Quae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam diligens negligentia</hi> and ſuch might bee ſeene in him by his frequent vſing the barbarous word <hi>Oſſum</hi> for a <hi>Bone,</hi> rather then the word <hi>Os,</hi> for (ſaith he) <hi>Mallem vt repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendant grammatici, quàm vt non intelligant populi:</hi> Hee ſtood not ſo much on his <hi>Owne Credit</hi> as his <hi>Peoples profit.</hi> When we haue ſpent our time, and paines in knots, and flouriſhes, ſtudying rather after <hi>Fine phraſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>Confeſſ.</hi> 1. 14.</note> then <hi>Mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> it may be ſaid of vs, as the ſame Father ſaith of <hi>Homer,</hi> that he was <hi>dulciſſimè vanus,</hi> Yea we ſhall ſay in the end as one doth of his owne labours, <hi>quod ad vſum luſi,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auſonius in monoſyl.</note> 
               <hi>quod ad moleſtiam laboraui:</hi> In reſpect of the profit comes by them, they are but Sport; in reſpect of the paines in making and gathering, they are ſore Labour and Sweat.</p>
            <p>As this Extreme; ſo that otherwiſe, in dealing with the Word of God too <hi>Looſely</hi> and <hi>Superficially,</hi> muſt carefully be auoided. Though we may not <hi>Slauiſhly</hi> tie our ſelues to words, yet we may not neglect to ſpeake <hi>Wiſely</hi> and <hi>as becommeth the Oracles of God.</hi> Our phraſe it muſt bee <hi>apta</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) though not <hi>alta.</hi> Many mens la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bours are deſpiſed through neglect of this; whoſe paines for the <hi>Matter</hi> might be well approued of, but the Slouen-like handling of it, turnes the ſtomacke. Do we not loath the meate (though otherwiſe good and wholeſome) that is ſerued in, in a ſluttiſh diſh?</p>
            <p>Be not too baſe; vſe no fooliſh termes, nor ridiculous. Thoſe <hi>Knots</hi> which are performed with the <hi>Celerity</hi> of the <hi>Hand,</hi> are Commendable in <hi>Clearkely writing:</hi> Many <hi>Speake well</hi> by <hi>Nature;</hi> Many by <hi>Industrie</hi> and <hi>Art</hi> attaine vnto it: as <hi>Demoſthenes</hi> who came to that excellent faculty of ſpeaking as that he could leade his Auditory, to what part he pleaſed, by ſpending more <hi>Oyle</hi> then <hi>Wine</hi> (as himſelfe telleth one who asked him how he attained thereto.) <hi>Scripture</hi> it ſelfe approues of a godly <hi>Eloquence,</hi> let not vs deſpiſe it, but bleſſe God for ſuch an excellent gift, where it is beſtowed.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:16605:11"/>Beloued, I am farre from being a <hi>Patron</hi> for <hi>Idleneſſe,</hi> giue me leaue to ſpeake the truth; There are ſome of good hopes, who vpon their firſt entry into the Miniſtery, to auoid the imputation of <hi>Dumb-dogs,</hi> ſo farre breake ſilence, as that if they preach not twice euery Sabboth, preſently conceit they are as no body, and ſhall looſe reſpect; which is a cauſe of venting many raw, and vndigeſted meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons. He who is able to receiue it, let him receiue it, and honour that day with <hi>Two young Pigeons,</hi> or <hi>Two young Turtle doues;</hi> Let him follow that Councell the Wiſeman giues, <hi>In the morning ſowe thy ſeede, and in the euening with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold not thine hand, for thou knoweſt not whether ſhall proſper, either this or that,</hi>
               <note place="margin">i. e. Nuper plan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tatus &amp; eccleſia inſitus, quales, erant Catechu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meni.</note> 
               <hi>or whether they both ſhall be alike good, Eccl.</hi> 11.6. But as for him who is <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> a young ſcholler and new entered into the work, let them not take too much vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, but remember the Councell the people of Rome gaue, who hearing that ſome of their <hi>Colonies</hi> waxed bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ren, willed that the husbandmen ſhould <hi>melius arare &amp; &amp; minus ſerere;</hi> So take me rightly, and I am ſure you can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not count the Councell to be vngodly: Let ſuch as cannot preach <hi>Often,</hi> and <hi>Well</hi> too, ſpend more time in their <hi>Stu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dies,</hi> and leſſe time in their <hi>Pulpits:</hi> And for a while be con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent to gather herbes to make pottage for Gods hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhould, wherein alſo they had need bee very circumſpect that they gather not <hi>wild-gourds</hi> in ſtead of <hi>wholeſome herbs.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Secondly, we muſt hold our <hi>Pen</hi> vpon the <hi>Full</hi> for that is, moſt proper. Faſten not vpon Scripture any other ſenſe, then the nature of the place will beare. You know the Councell that the <hi>Prieſts &amp; Diuiners</hi> gaue vnto the <hi>Princes of the Philiſtins,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Sam. 6 9.</note> concerning the <hi>Arke: If it goe by the way of its owne coaſt to Bethſhemeſh then it is from God, but if it goe another way</hi> (if it bee vrged and goaded on) <hi>it is but a matter of Chance,</hi> Of mans wit and inuention. Beware we, I beſeech you, how we dare to wreſt the Scriptures, and (as <hi>Chymickes</hi> with <hi>Naturall bodies</hi>) by torturing them, endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour to extract that out, which neither <hi>God</hi> nor <hi>Nature</hi>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:16605:11"/>
hath put into them. This I rather beſeech you, to be warie of, by how much we are the more apt to fall into it, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the <hi>Countenancing</hi> of our own <hi>Rotten fancies.</hi> He that is wedded to an Opinion, and hath Wit to maintaine it, ſhall neuer want ſome Scripture, which (with a little woing) may ſeeme to Countenance it. It was (you know) the boaſt of one <hi>Chryſippus,</hi> of whom <hi>Laertius</hi> makes men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, that he often wanted opinions to aduance, but once hauing an opinion, he neuer wanted Arguments to defend it. It is a miſerable praiſe to bee a wittie diſturber of the Churches peace; And yet, this is the onely praiſe that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny doe affect, who hauing once faſtened vpon ſome Aſſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion (though neuer ſo abſurd) think it their glory to defend it, Conceiting all that they ſee, or heare, or reade,<note place="margin">Antiphorus Orietes.</note> makes for it: Like him in <hi>Aristotle,</hi> who where euer he went, he thought he ſaw the picture of himſelfe. Thus wee reade of <hi>Adrian</hi> the <hi>Pope,</hi> who when the Contentions were be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the ſeruices of Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi> and Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iacob. de Vorag. in vita Greg.</note> which ſhould take place, by common conſent both the maſſe-bookes were laid vpon Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Altar, expecting the deciſion of that doubt by Reuelation: The Church dores being opened in the morning, Saint <hi>Gregories</hi> maſſe-booke was rent, and torne in many pieces, and lay ſcattered about the Church, but Saint <hi>Ambroſe's</hi> lay whole and open vpon the Altar: which euent, one would haue thought, ſhould haue ſignified thus much; that the Maſſe of <hi>Gregory</hi> ſhould be Cancelled and aboliſhed, and that of <hi>Ambroſe</hi> authenticall, and allowed: But now Pope <hi>Adrian</hi> (who was for <hi>Gregory</hi>) expounds it thus: that the renting and ſcattering of <hi>Gregories</hi> miſſal, intended the diſperſing of it ouer all the Chriſtian world, and that it ſhould bee onely receiued as Canonicall. Such another was that Fryar, who finding out <hi>Maria</hi> in the Scripture vſed plurally for Seas, cryed out, that hee had found in the Old Teſtament the name of <hi>Maria</hi> for the <hi>Virgin Mary.</hi> What is this, but with the wicked ſonnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> to ſtrike our fleſh-hooke with yron teeth into the pot of Gods Sacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice;
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:16605:12"/>
and to account <hi>all ours,</hi> that it brings vp? And if in caſe the Scripture hath not for vs, ſo ſoone as wee de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire, to take by force, as they did from the <hi>Sacrificers?</hi> Yea what is this any other, then with the <hi>Harlot</hi> in the <hi>Kings,</hi> to lay the dead childe of our owne heads, and braines, in the boſome of the true mother the <hi>Holy Scriptures,</hi> and ſay it is hers? A ſinne in the iudgement of ſome of the <hi>Antient</hi> ſo fowle, as that (in their eſteeme) it deſerued to be ran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged in the ſame ranke with the ſin againſt the <hi>Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Other ſinnes ſeeme to be of weakeneſſe, but this of wit and ſtrength. Beſides he that ſeekes to faſten a new ſenſe on Scripture, indites another <hi>Scripture,</hi> (as it were) and ſo after a ſort makes himſelfe a <hi>God.</hi> A rule of ſpeciall vſe; forget it not.</p>
            <p>And yet, while I ſpeake of holding our <hi>Pen</hi> directly vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the <hi>Full,</hi> miſtake me not, For it is requiſite ſometimes (as in the fetching of a Compaſſe) that it ſhould beare a little on the left ſide, that it may the better giue full where it ſhould, and ſmall alſo where it is required. Thus did <hi>Nathan</hi> in propounding of the <hi>Parable</hi> of the poore man with his little <hi>Ewe:</hi> Our Sauiour often by things feyned did ſet forth, and expreſſe vnfeined truths: Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> likewiſe fetch a compaſſe, the better to take his kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, holding his pen a little on the left ſide (as it were) <hi>Beleeueſt thou Agrippa? I know that thou beleeueſt.</hi> If euer any knew <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> to change his voice and to attemper his ſtile that he might profit, hee was the man: Yet many eſteeme this practiſe, no better then flatterie and lying; but I haſten.</p>
            <p>We haue done with thoſe Rules which Concerne the Ordering of our Pen; Now for thoſe which reſpect the <hi>Cariage of the Body,</hi> which if it be ſeemely, is a great grace to writing. The Particulars are theſe: 1. The <hi>Head</hi> muſt be held <hi>vpright,</hi> and looke ſtrait forward. 2. The <hi>Arme</hi> laid <hi>right forth</hi> vpon the Paper. 3. The <hi>Paper</hi> lie as <hi>neere to the midst of the Body,</hi> as the ſtrait holding forth of the Arme will permit, and ſuffer. For the Firſt.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:16605:12"/>
               <hi>Be thou an enſample</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothie) in life, in doctrine, in holy Conuerſation.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Tim. 4.12.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Exemplaris vita eſt concio optima</note> It is the <hi>Example</hi> wherein the force of the <hi>Rule</hi> doth lie: This our people eſpecially looke vpon, and accordingly conceiue, as <hi>Labans</hi> Cattell did among the <hi>Rods</hi> that <hi>Iacob</hi> laid in the <hi>Gutters</hi> before their eyes, <hi>Gen.</hi> 30. In which reſpect it was that God thus complained: <hi>From the Prophets of Ieruſalem, wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe is gone forth into all the land, Ier.</hi> 23.15. The ſinnes of Teachers are the Teachers of ſinnes, and therefore no mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uell if they be more odious vnto God, then the ſins of any of the people, which appeares by this, in that the Lord re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired in the old Law,<note place="margin">Leuit. 4.3.14.</note> as much ſacrifice for the Prieſts ſin alone, as he did for the ſins of all the Congregation beſides. The beſt <hi>Schooleman</hi> ſeemes to giue the reaſon; for when we ſinne we doe <hi>peccare in quid eſſentialiter,</hi> but others, <hi>in quale accidentaliter,</hi> therefore ours greater.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be yee holy</hi> therefore,<note place="margin">Iſay 52.11.</note> 
               <hi>you that doe beare the veſſels of the Lord,</hi> haue <hi>Feete</hi> to walke withall,<note place="margin">Pſal. 115.7.</note> as well as <hi>Mouthes</hi> to ſpeake withall, leaſt you bee found in the end, <hi>Idols</hi> as well as dumbe ones. You are here preſent with the enſignes of grauity vpon your backes; Seeing theſe buſhes hung forth, ſee there be good wine within. In a word, let vs ſo liue, as that we be <hi>Walking Sermons, Epiſtles,</hi> and <hi>Goſpels</hi> to thoſe amongſt whom we liue.</p>
            <p>Secondly, the <hi>Arme</hi> muſt be laid right-forth vpon the <hi>Paper</hi> on which we write. We may not haue reſpect of perſons in the deliuering of our meſſage. <hi>The Preacher ſought to finde out acceptable words and that which was written was vpright, euen words of truth, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.10. For <hi>Manner,</hi> it would doe well, to take vp ſuch words as may giue law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full content, and be beſt accepted; But for <hi>Matter</hi> let them be <hi>words of truth,</hi> &amp; that which is written let it be <hi>vpright,</hi> without fauouring of any mans Corruptions or Vices. The <hi>Poore</hi> may not be neglected, ſeeing Chriſt's blood was ſhed as well for the <hi>Belfry</hi> as for the <hi>Chancell;</hi> Nor may the <hi>Great</hi> be ſpared, much leſſe poyſoned by <hi>Flatterie.</hi> It was ſaid of old, <hi>Few great mens Confeſſors will get to heauen:</hi> For
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:16605:13"/>
how great ſoeuer the ſins of great men are, ſtill they goe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way with <hi>Abſolution,</hi> and it would doe well now, if we would be faithfull, and if at any time A Lord ſhould aske his Chaplaine, as Chriſt did his, <hi>whom doe men ſay that I am?</hi>
               <note place="margin">Matth. 16.13.</note> let the anſwer be according to the truth; Some ſay you are thus my Lord, and ſome ſay thus, &amp;c. that if in Caſe they heare ill, they may labour to cut off all iuſt occaſions of ſuch report; If well, endeauour to preſerue, and deſerue the ſame to <hi>Gods</hi> and his <hi>Goſpels</hi> honour.</p>
            <p>But this I muſt tell you withall, that <hi>Good manners</hi> muſt be obſerued in ſpeaking to our <hi>Betters,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5.1, 2. <hi>Acts</hi> 26. (notwithſtanding that ciuill, and well nurtured lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage be eſteemed by ſome that are ouer-ſowre, and rigid, to bee a daubing with vntempered morter, and nothing thought to bee zealouſly ſpoken, but what is vnciuill and rude.) <hi>Dauid</hi> (as <hi>Bernard</hi> obſerues) could brooke it well enough, that <hi>Nathan</hi> ſhould tell him of his ſin, but he could not endure <hi>Shemei's</hi> rebukes, though it was for the ſame of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fence (And he ſaw God in it too) The Reaſon he renders to be this; <hi>Nathan</hi> did doe it with reuerence, and reſpect vnto the perſon of the King; But <hi>Shemei</hi> behaued himſelfe vnreuerently, and fell to downe right railing.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, the <hi>Paper</hi> we write vpon, muſt be laid as <hi>nigh the breaſt,</hi> as may be. Thoſe we <hi>Admoniſh, Reproue, Inſtruct, &amp;c.</hi> muſt be neare our hearts; All we doe muſt bee done in <hi>Loue.</hi> Thus Saint <hi>Paul</hi> with the ſame breath calleth the <hi>Galatians fooliſh</hi> and yet <hi>Brethren,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Gal. 4.</note> and <hi>little children;</hi> giuing ſignes of the greateſt loue vnto them that could bee: the like was his manner of dealing with the <hi>Corinthians.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.2.</note> A good conceit of the <hi>Phyſitian,</hi> wee ſay, is halfe the cure: When our people are perſwaded of our Affection towards them, then it is likely our paines will be auaileable. I per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue I muſt haſten; I come now to thoſe <hi>Rules</hi> which concerne <hi>the worke it ſelfe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here three things are obſerued by good Pen-men; <hi>Ratio, Modus Species;</hi> the former doth concerne the <hi>Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue part,</hi> And the two later the <hi>Practique parts of Writing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:16605:13"/>The <hi>Reaſon</hi> muſt bee found out, and rendered why the letter is made thus, not thus; and being made this way, is more gracefull, then being made that way, or that; And ſo for the Coniunction, knitting and ioyning together of them, without the vnderſtanding whereof, hardly ſhall a man euer write well.</p>
            <p>Thus, muſt <hi>Gods Scribes</hi> bee able to ſhew <hi>Grounds</hi> for what they doe and teach.<note place="margin">1. <hi>Ratio.</hi>
               </note> I do not meane that a Miniſter ſhould be ſtrictly tyed, to render the <hi>Reaſon</hi> of euery <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> he doth deliuer: A Courſe though <hi>Profitable,</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſefull,</hi> yet not euer <hi>Neceſſary.</hi> True it is, there is <hi>Reaſon</hi> for all Gods Commandements, if we could ſee it, but we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not alwaies conceiue that <hi>Reaſon;</hi> And if wee ſhould be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeue no more then we can giue <hi>Reaſon</hi> for, wee ſhall not beleeue halfe that which a Chriſtian is bound to beleeue to his ſoules ſaluation. The Councell that Saint <hi>Auſtin</hi> giues to his Scholler <hi>Licentius</hi> concerning thoſe things he heard of him, would be remembred, <hi>Nolo te cauſas rationeſ<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> rimari, quae etiamſi reddi poſſint fidej tamen qua mihi credis non eas debeo:</hi> If thus, concerning thoſe things he taught him, then much more concerning thoſe things, which God teacheth vs. The Reaſons and Grounds of them though they might be giuen (which yet as I ſay concerning diuers Articles of our Faith cannot) yet it ſuits not well with that credit and truſt which we owe vnto God, too curiouſly to ſearch in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to, or call into queſtion: But my meaning is, we ſhould be <hi>Grounded</hi> and <hi>Iudicious Textmen,</hi> And be able to ſay as <hi>Iohn</hi> 3.11. <hi>we ſpeake that we know,</hi> And with Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſ.</hi> 1.5. <hi>Our Goſpell comes vnto you not in word onely, but in power, and in much aſſurance.</hi> We are firſt, exactly to know the truth, and then deliuer it vnto Gods people. The Sermons of the <hi>Prophet Nahum</hi> are called,<note place="margin">Nah. 1.1. <hi>Prooem. in Nahu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  </hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>the booke of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons:</hi> the <hi>Reaſon Hierome</hi> giues (and me thinkes it is a paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing good one) becauſe ſaith he, he well vnderſtood, and ſaw, whatſoeuer he ſaid. Hence it is that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> cries <hi>Shame on them</hi> who deſire to bee <hi>Teachers of the Law,</hi> vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtanding neither <hi>what they ſay, nor whereof they affirme,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.7.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:16605:14"/>A great fault therefore it is in young Diuines, to ſcorne the <hi>Catechiſme</hi> affecting a profounder kinde of learning, (as they conceiue) plodding in <hi>Poſtills</hi> and <hi>Controuerſies,</hi> and <hi>raw in Principles;</hi> Taking the greateſt myſteries of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion fitteſt Arguments for the exerciſing of their wits,<note place="margin">In his Chryſo. paſſus.</note> As <hi>Eckius</hi> who diſcuſſing the queſtion of <hi>Predeſtination,</hi> in the very enterance of his diſcourſe, giues his Reaſon why he vndertooke that Argument, for that he thought it to be the fitteſt queſtion, in which he might <hi>Iuueniles calores exercere;</hi> When we know a wiſe man will chooſe to deale with <hi>Woodden waſters,</hi> before he plaies at <hi>Sharpe.</hi> An error in the <hi>Foundation,</hi> puts the whole building in apparent ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zard. Therefore it ſhall be your wiſedome, who are ſons of the Prophets, firſt to aske Councell of <hi>Caluins</hi> (or ſome others) learned <hi>Institutions:</hi> to peruſe well the booke of the <hi>Articles of our Religion,</hi> and the <hi>Bookes of Homilies,</hi> as our Church enioyneth; that what you deliuer for <hi>Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> may be comprehended in <hi>Eſſence, Substance, Effect,</hi> or <hi>Naturall inference</hi> with ſome one of them. But of all the <hi>Sheaues</hi> let the <hi>Bible</hi> haue preheminence, and let the reſt of the <hi>Shocke</hi> doe obeiſance vnto it. Nor let young <hi>Cockerills</hi> which newly begin to <hi>Crowe,</hi> be ſetting vpon the great <hi>Cocks of Game,</hi> billing at that Sophiſticall <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> or at that Iudicious Interpreter <hi>Caluin,</hi> audaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly controuling him, fooliſhly deſpiſing their great skill, and learning: Nor run raſhly vpon the point of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> before they know (it may bee) what the name meaneth. Better by many degrees it is, to let theſe things alone, till they be growne in Iudgement, and able to ſpeake of them to purpoſe,<note place="margin">2. <hi>Modus.</hi>
               </note> without wronging either themſelues, or the Cauſe.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Manner</hi> of making euery letter, would be knowne, as well as the <hi>Ground</hi> or <hi>Reaſon.</hi> Let a <hi>Scribe</hi> begin to frame his letters, after a Corrupt, and Contrary way, (as to begin at the heele when hee ſhould begin at the head) will hee euer proue good <hi>Pen-man?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Would we be the <hi>Ornaments</hi> of our <hi>Pulpets,</hi> and haue
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:16605:14"/>
the praiſe of being good <hi>Ezra's</hi> apt and readie Scribes? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin we then methodically. <hi>The wiſe Preacher taught the people knowledge, yea he gaue good heed, and ſought out, and ſet in order many Prouerbs, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.9. God hath deuided his Word into fit parts, and ordered it to our Capacitie, and Vnderſtanding; It belongeth (therefore) vnto Gods Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters to gather out of this treaſure things <hi>both New and Old,</hi> and like good <hi>Stewards</hi> ſet them forth before Gods family in the beſt order that they can, beginning firſt with <hi>milke</hi> and ſpoone-meate, after the Apoſtles practiſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 5.13. It is a prepoſterous courſe for any (be they themſelues neuer ſo learned) comming to an ignorant peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and ſuperſtitious, (for they are ſeldome ſeuered) to be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gin with <hi>Controuerſie:</hi> Let vs firſt teach the <hi>Principles</hi> plainely, and diligently, and after a familiar manner by <hi>Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion</hi> and <hi>Anſwer,</hi> and ſpend one part of the <hi>Lords-day</hi> (Commonly called <hi>Sunday</hi>) in this Courſe, for as much as there is ſtill need; New-commers on. You know it was the practiſe of the <hi>Primitiue times,</hi> the <hi>Apoſtles</hi> had their <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſme, Heb.</hi> 6. Where you haue the Name how it was called <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>prima Christianiſmi principia</hi> (as <hi>Beza</hi> renders it) <hi>The Principles of the Doctrine of Chriſt,</hi> as our Tranſlation (truly) hath it. And the <hi>Heads</hi> or <hi>Principles</hi> themſelues therein contained, and handled: In number ſixe after the ordinary account.</p>
            <p n="1">1. <hi>Repentance from dead workes] i. e.</hi> the doctrine of mans miſery, the knowledge whereof comes by the <hi>Law, Rom.</hi> 7.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Faith towards God]</hi> The doctrine of mans deliuery; the ſumme whereof is contained in the <hi>Apoſtles Creed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>The Doctrine of Baptiſmes]</hi> That is of the <hi>Sacraments: Baptiſmes</hi> (by a trope) being but for both; And (beſides the trope) both the <hi>Inward baptiſme of Chriſt,</hi> and the <hi>Out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> of <hi>Iohn, i. e.</hi> Chriſt's Miniſters, being thereby noted.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Laying on of hands]</hi> An ancient Ceremonie vſed both in the time of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Goſpell,</hi> in ſundry Caſes: 1. In hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of the ſicke, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.40. <hi>Marke</hi> 16.18. 2. In ordaining
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:16605:15"/>
of Miniſters, <hi>Acts</hi> 13.3. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.14. <hi>&amp;</hi> 5.22. 3. In Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferring the gifts of the <hi>Holy Ghoſt, Acts</hi> 8.17. <hi>&amp;</hi> 19.5. 4. In Bleſſing of Children, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48.14. <hi>Matth.</hi> 19.13. <hi>Luke</hi> 18.15. The <hi>Manner</hi> was: The Children of the Faithfull be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Catechized, were to make open and publike Confeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of the former <hi>Principles, viz.</hi> of their <hi>Repentance;</hi> Of their <hi>Faith;</hi> Of the <hi>Sacraments,</hi> and after this they had hands lay'd vpon them, and were Confirmed to be of the Couenant of God, and of the viſible Church. A Ceremo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie which (through the long neglect thereof) is much ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted againſt and carped at, but may bee wiſhed that it were vſed oftener then it is and more reſpected, which (the due cautions being obſerued, and it freed (as with vs it is) from ſuperſtitious abuſe) it well deſerues. Now vnder this Head the <hi>Ministerie</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> may bee Comprehended.</p>
            <p n="5">5. <hi>Reſurrection from the dead]</hi> Albeit they ſhould die, and their bodies be lay'd in the earth, yet that at the laſt day their bodies ſhould be raiſed vp to life againe.</p>
            <p n="6">6. <hi>Eternall Iudgement]</hi> And <hi>that euery one ſhould receiue in their bodies, that which they haue done, be it good or euill, Eccleſ.</hi> 12.14. Theſe two laſt Heads, being made diſtinct, and howeuer (happily) handled vnder the ſecond <hi>Principle</hi> the <hi>Doctrine of Faith,</hi> yet here beaten particularly vpon by the <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> for theſe two reaſons: 1. For that they were <hi>derided by the Gentiles:</hi> 2. For that they were the <hi>hope of Christians.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As the <hi>Apostles,</hi> ſo had the <hi>Ancient Fathers,</hi> after them, their <hi>Introductions to Religion. Clemens Alexadrinus</hi> his <hi>Pedagogus; Lactantius</hi> his <hi>Inſtitutions; Cyrill</hi> his <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſmes; Auguſtine</hi> his <hi>Enchyridion;</hi> and booke <hi>de catechi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zandis rudibus.</hi> And ſo hath euery Church in Chriſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome:<note place="margin">Maſter Yates his Modell of Diuinity, in his Epiſt. ded. to the Church of England.</note> And ours amongſt the reſt, which (to vſe the words of a Reuerend and Iudicious Diuine) <hi>is like Samp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons haire faire and ſtrong; Strong in precepts; beautifull in method; And therein carry's away, the honour from other formes. For whereas ſome teach the Commandements before
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:16605:15"/>
the Creed (as if they would teach a man to goe before he liue) Others put the Seales in the midſt of their writings (as if that which ſeales all, ſhould not hang at the bottome of the bill or bond) Our method is to begin with Faith, by which we liue, then to come to the Law of life, by which we walke; After this it leads vs to Prayer, least we ſhould faint in faith or waxe wearie of workes: And laſtly finding faith but weake, obedience im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfect, and prayers not as they ſhould be, it brings vs to Gods ſeales as the ſafetie and ſecurity of all our eſtate.</hi> Thus farre hee.</p>
            <p>Now then, <hi>Good Fathers</hi> and <hi>Brethren,</hi> pittie the miſcar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying of many a ſoule, vnder your Charges, for want of <hi>Method.</hi> And giue eare to that Counſell which that <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered Father, Biſhop Babington,</hi> in <hi>Leuit.</hi> 7. doth giue vnto you; <hi>Art thou a Miniſter called of God? &amp;c. ſubmit your ſelfe to the profit of your people, hunt not after your owne glory that you are ſo learned, eloquent, and profound: If your people profit not, becauſe you flie too high a pitch for them, and ſcorne to lay a foundation of the Catechiſme amongſt them, you will be found at the reckoning day, an vnprofitable ſeruant, and one that hath gained nothing to his Lord, but hath hid his talent in the fowle napkin of fruitleſſe matter, and idle figures of affected ſpeech.</hi> Thinke of that Charge giuen by the <hi>Arch-Biſhop</hi> of our ſoules, <hi>Feed my Lambes; Feed my Sheepe:</hi> His <hi>Lambes</hi> firſt, and why ſo? Surely for that the encreaſe and welfare of the <hi>Flocke</hi> depends on them; If they be ſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feted, or ſtarued, the <hi>Flocke</hi> ſhall neuer thriue nor proſper.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Papiſts,</hi> in their preface to the <hi>Catechiſme</hi> of the <hi>Councell of Trent,</hi> confeſſe, that all the ground which we haue got of them, hath beene by Cetechizing, and ſhall wee againe looſe that ground through our neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect? <hi>Iulian</hi> himſelfe could not deuiſe a readier way to ouerthrow <hi>Chriſtian Religion</hi> then by pulling downe <hi>Schooles,</hi> and ouerthrowing thoſe <hi>Places</hi> where Children were religiouſly educated, and catechized. Let vs effectu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally conſider of theſe things, and be no longer like to ſome vndiſcreet, and fooliſh maſter, who to pleaſe a fond and
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:16605:16"/>
ouerweening parent, marres the progreſſe of a childe, in raiſing him vp to a higher <hi>Forme</hi> and <hi>Author</hi> before hee hath learned his firſt <hi>Rules of Grammer:</hi> What followes vpon this?</p>
            <p>But, firſt a loſſe of our owne paines and labours. Looke on him that preacheth twice or thrice a weeke, and ſo hath continued for many yeares together, omitting Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chizing of his People, and tell me, if hee hath reaped ſo much fruit of his long labours, as ſome one hath done of one yeares paines, who hath ioyned both together.</p>
            <p>Secondly, An emptie oſtentation in the Hearer; A raſh cenſuring of <hi>Church-Gouernement</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> through heate of <hi>Affection</hi> and want of <hi>Iudgement.</hi> Cenſorious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors, are ignorant profeſſors; try it when you pleaſe, this you ſhall finde, that thoſe who ſpend their zeale this way, haue not wherewith to anſwer you if you queſtion with them about <hi>Fundamentall Points.</hi> For as the <hi>Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pher</hi> teacheth of mad, and phantaſticall men, they are very apprehenſiue of all outward accidents, becauſe their ſoules are inwardly emptie, and vnfurniſhed of any thing of worth, which might hold the inward attention of their minds, and might ballance it, and keepe it vpright againſt all outward occurrents whatſoeuer. I haſten to a Conclu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, and come to the <hi>Third</hi> and laſt thing obſeruable in <hi>Writing,</hi> wherein indeed the <hi>Subſtance</hi> of it doth Conſiſt, and that is the <hi>Species.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Should a man bee able to giue the <hi>Reaſon;</hi> Shew the <hi>Manner</hi> of making euery letter; yet vnleſſe he giue it its full <hi>Proportion</hi> and <hi>Shape,</hi> he doth looſe his praiſe: For that giueth life, and ſpirit to his writing. Here the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticulars</hi> conſiderable are many, I will content my ſelfe with ſome few.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The <hi>Sizing</hi> of the letter would be looked vnto, that the <hi>Depth</hi> and <hi>Fulneſſe</hi> bee <hi>Proportionable.</hi> To bee euer preaching <hi>Law,</hi> and harping vpon the ſad ſtring of <hi>Iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment,</hi> is not well. Wee beare the name of <hi>Spirituall men,</hi> if then we be wanting in the <hi>Comforting part</hi> of our office,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:16605:16"/>
where is the Spirit, that we haue our denomination from? The <hi>Spirit</hi> is the <hi>Comforter,</hi> if then a Miniſter can, or doe ſay little to the Comfort of diſtreſſed conſciences, may it not be queſtioned where this ſpirit is? Looke vpon the <hi>Prophets, Apoſtles,</hi> and <hi>Christ</hi> himſelfe, and you ſhall ſee what great care they had alwaies, that the fulneſſe of ioy might be anſwerable to the depth of ſorrow, in thoſe they had to deale withall, <hi>Exod.</hi> 14.13. 2 <hi>Kings</hi> 19.6. <hi>Iſay</hi> 50.4. <hi>Matth.</hi> 5.12. <hi>Luke</hi> 4.18. <hi>Iohn</hi> 14.1. <hi>Rom.</hi> 5.1. <hi>&amp;</hi> 8.32. <hi>Phil.</hi> 4.4.</p>
            <p n="2">2. <hi>Whites</hi> muſt be obſerued; this doth grace our writing much. Diſcerne we betwixt <hi>Sheepe</hi> and <hi>Wolues:</hi> In our <hi>Sheepe,</hi> betwixt the <hi>wholeſome,</hi> and <hi>vnſound:</hi> In the <hi>Vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſound,</hi> betwixt the <hi>Weake</hi> and <hi>Tainted:</hi> In the <hi>Tainted</hi> betwixt the <hi>Natures, Qualities,</hi> and <hi>Degrees</hi> of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection. God much complaines of the want of this in the <hi>Shepheards of Iſrael, Ezek.</hi> 34. they did not diſcerne be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the <hi>weake</hi> and <hi>ſtrong,</hi> the <hi>cleane</hi> and <hi>vncleane</hi> to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed accordingly: Let vs haue a ſpeciall regard herein, that we breake not bruiſed reeds, nor make the hearts of the <hi>Righteous ſad</hi> within them. Some are ignorantly miſled, as thoſe who went with <hi>Abſolom</hi> from <hi>Ieruſalem,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2 Sam. 15.</note> and were vnwittingly made Simple <hi>Rebels,</hi> their hearts being free from any plot againſt their <hi>Soueraigne:</hi> The ſimplicity of ſuch is as worthy of pittie, as their miſguidance of indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation.; Reduce we them. Some are entangled with <hi>doubtfull diſputations,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Rom. 14.1.</note> and haue their conſciences enſnared with conceits and ſubtilties, who are docible and tractable of themſelues, not obſtinate and wilfull; <hi>Receiue we them, Rom.</hi> 14.1. While there appeares a true deſire, and godly endeauour to bee better informed, let them not bee too hardly dealt withall, nor puniſhment and compulſion ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtened. But as for thoſe that ſinne of <hi>malicious wickedneſſe be not mercifull vnto thoſe men.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But how will you diſtinguiſh?<note place="margin">Quest.</note>
            </p>
            <p>How know you a <hi>Hunger-bitten Beggar</hi> from a <hi>Canting Rogue?</hi> one <hi>ſpeakes with Supplications,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reſp.</note> and is thankefull for
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:16605:17"/>
the leaſt fauours; the other you may know by his Rhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>toricall ſtyle. In the one hand hee hath his <hi>Petition,</hi> in the other hand a <hi>Stone.</hi> Theſe things may the <hi>Church</hi> likewiſe, as well as <hi>Church-men,</hi> be pleaſed to take notice of in her <hi>Cenſures,</hi> for this is a third Rule giuen, which you ſee I am fallen vpon.</p>
            <p n="3">3. <hi>Preſſe not too much</hi> on that part of the letter, which requires a <hi>fauourable touch,</hi> nor bee <hi>ſparing</hi> in that part, which requires the <hi>contrarie.</hi> There is one courſe in our Miniſterie to bee held with <hi>nouices,</hi> and ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to bee held with thoſe who are of <hi>riper yeares,</hi> towards the one ſort <hi>mother-like indulgence,</hi> towards the other, <hi>father-like grauitie.</hi> Thus much is taught vs in that <hi>Allegorie</hi> vſed by our <hi>Sauiour,</hi> of <hi>Wine</hi> and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſells,</hi> by way of <hi>Apologie</hi> for his more <hi>Mildeneſſe</hi> in his <hi>Iniunctions,</hi> then <hi>Iohn</hi> vſed to his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9.17. Impoſe wee not too heauie taskes vpon new commers on, nor diſcourage wee them with ouer great auſterity:<note place="margin">In Rom. 14. Verſe 4.</note> It is a good ſpeech of <hi>Caluin, Sem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per bene ſperemus de eo in quo ceruimus aliquid Dej.</hi> So <hi>Bucer</hi> reſolued to refuſe none in whom he ſaw <hi>aliquid Chriſti.</hi> Who ſo is wiſe, let him conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p n="4">4. <hi>Keeepe your diſtances,</hi> betwixt <hi>letter</hi> and <hi>letter, word</hi> and <hi>word.</hi> There is a time for all things vnder the Sunne (ſaith <hi>Solomon, Eccleſ.</hi> 3.1.) So a time for <hi>Hearing,</hi> A time for <hi>Reading;</hi> Another for <hi>Praying, &amp;c.</hi> All are Gods Ordinances, one may not iuſtle out the other, but each is to haue its time and turne, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9.3. and ſerued in its Courſe, by Gods <hi>Stewards,</hi> for the feaſting of his Family, who euer haue good ſtomackes, and like hungry men feed vpon euery diſh that is before them. Serue in <hi>Gods Commandements;</hi> ſet before them which you will, they are for it. If the Firſt Commandement, they will feed, <hi>Lord haue mercy on me incline my heart to this Law.</hi> If the Second, or the Third, their ſtomacke ſtands alike good to all. Or if you commend vnto them <hi>Prayer</hi> with the ſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall Requeſts to be made; If for themſelues, For <hi>Loue,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:16605:17"/>
Faith, Feare, Repentance, &amp;c.</hi> you ſhall haue them at it, <hi>wee beſeech thee to heare vs good Lord.</hi> Or if ſuch like graces are to be beg'd for others, they continue alike zealous, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uout, calling to God for Audience: Pitty it is then to withhold any of Gods allowance from his houſhold. We condemne the <hi>Papists</hi> (and that iuſtly) of a kinde of Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>criledge, in withholding the Cup from Gods people, and can we be innocent if we detaine any part of that which is allowed; The laying of our people ſo much to one <hi>Breaſt</hi> without an orderly giuing of the other, I am perſwaded, is a cauſe that God in many Congregations dryeth vp that Breaſt that was ſo (in a manner) altogether drawne at, that the other may not grow dry; He cloſeth vp the wombe of her who was fruitfull, that ſhee who was barren may reioyce and no more be called Barren. One<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly one thing more is wanting to make vs abſolute <hi>Pen-men,</hi> And that is</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ioyne and vnite your letters</hi> together in an orderly and comely manner, Firſt, <hi>Chriſt</hi> and <hi>Man, Coloſ.</hi> 2.19. Second<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man, Iohn</hi> 17.21. 1 <hi>Iohn</hi> 1.3. Thirdly, <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Angels, Coloſ.</hi> 1.20. Fourthly, <hi>Man</hi> and <hi>Man, Iſay</hi> 11.6, 7, 8. As the Hearts of <hi>Husbands,</hi> and <hi>Wiues; Parents</hi> and <hi>Children; Neighbour</hi> and <hi>Neighbour; Maieſtrates</hi> and <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects; Prince</hi> and <hi>People, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Theſe Rules obſerued, we ſhall be <hi>Compleate Scribes</hi> in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed; And when as other ſhall ſtand in need of <hi>Letters Teſtimoniall</hi> to others, and from others, as did thoſe falſe <hi>Apoſtles,</hi> 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 3.1. we ſhall need to goe no further then to our <hi>Flocks</hi> and <hi>People,</hi> ſaying of them, as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> did of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>Corinth,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1 Cor. 3.2.</note> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>You are our Epiſtle;</hi> yea better then any letters Commendatory wrote with <hi>Inke</hi> and <hi>Paper</hi> can be; for they run here, and there, and may ſoone be loſt; but our Praiſe is written, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> wherein wee doe inwardly reioyce; or rather <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>in cordibus veſtris,</hi> neuer to bee blot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted out. And whereas other Epiſtles in Hebrew, Greeke, or Latine, are read of none but ſuch as vnderſtand
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:16605:18"/>
the Languages. This Epiſtle is vnderſtood and read, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Of all men,</hi> Of what <hi>Nation</hi> ſoeuer. I haue done, and now deſcend the <hi>Mount,</hi> to take my ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding at the bottome of the <hi>Hill</hi> amongſt my Brethren. But firſt let vs Commend all to Gods good bleſſing, as our mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Church hath taught vs. Grant we beſeech thee Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mighty God, that the words which wee haue heard this day, &amp;c.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:16605:18"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
